# **Pedro Santos**

+34660167242 • pedro.santos.personal@gmail.com • www.linkedin.com/in/pedros • Madrid, Community of Madrid, Spain

#### **Professional Profile**

Software Engineer with 20+ years leading high-performing software teams and driving technical excellence. I specialize in Code renovation and modernization, DDD, TDD, Refactoring, software architecture, Test Automation, CI/CD, code quality, and technical processes to accelerate delivery and improve code quality. As the author of Agile Technical Practices Distilled, I empower organizations to master agile engineering and achieve measurable improvements in their processes.

# **Work Experience**

Distinguished Engineer

01/2023 – Present

Barcelona

- Working as a domain Tech Lead and as a technical coach in the Marketing domain.
- I love the mix of delivery and coaching. This keeps my feet solid on the ground and, at the same time, allows me to help improve the software engineering practices in Vista.

Co-Founder- CTO

CoKaiDo

01/2019 - 12/2022

Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain

- CoKaiDM defines itself as a technology talent accelerator.
- We designed a training path to help companies reach the highest quality standards in software development and IT Engineering practices, based on the book "Agile Technical Practices Distilled" written by our co-founder Pedro Santos.
- Projects: Voxel Technical coach (2019-2020) Wallapop Technical coach (2019-2020) LIFULL Connect Technical coach (2019-2020) AudienseCo Technical coach (2020) Iberia · IAG Lead Software Architect (2022)

#### Principal Software Engineer

11/2020 - 04/2022

Vista

**Vista** 

Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain

- · Working as a squad Lead in Personalization and as a technical coach across the organization.
- Work on the squad level is mostly front end in REACT and Typescript, using Terraform to deploy to AWS. Backend work is mostly in GoLang using AWS Lambdas and other AWS infrastructure.
- Love the mix of delivery work and coaching work. This keeps my feet solid on the ground and at the same time allows me to help improve the software engineering practices in Vista.

#### Principal Software Engineer

03/2018 - 12/2018

ASOS.com

London, United Kingdom

- Responsible for Software Engineering across ASOS E-commerce platform (Orders, Bag, Pricing, and Promotions).
- I work closely with teams to identify and implement best tools, technologies, and practices.
- Coach, mentor and empower software engineers on technical practices, object-oriented design, refactoring legacy applications, testing
  practices, design and architecture decisions, and career development.

#### **Principal Consultant**

06/2014 - 03/2018

Codurance

London, United Kingdom

- Redesigned the Codurance apprenticeship program. A 3-month full-time hands-on program focused on code, design, and architecture. Run the first iteration of the program.
- Moonpig (January 2018 March 2018) Run a software craft program on XP technical practices.
- Mango https://shop.mango.com (September 2017 November 2017) Worked as a consultant helping design a migration strategy from a monolith ecommerce solution to a distributed cloud-based solution
- ASOS www.asos.com (May 2015 August 2017) Principal Software Engineer in the warehouse and logistics platform. Principal Software Engineer in the web platform. Created and delivered the ASOS software craftsmanship program.
- Societe Generale (London) www.societegenerale.co.uk (June 2014 April 2015) Worked as an embedded software crafter in teams to help improve their development processes by continuously training and mentoring them in XP practices.

Founder, developer 09/2010 – 12/2016

**LetsBasket** Barcelona

- I have a few apps published in Apples's app store and Googles's Google Play.
- https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/letsbasket+-your-hoop-stats/id460185648
- https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/football-stats-more-lets4football+/id593996707
- https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/letscompref/id769406191

Tech Lead 12/2012 – 06/2014

Global Radio UK

Reading, UK

- · Order processing system.
- In this project I was responsible for leading/coaching/ mentoring Software Engineers making sure the work was delivered while meeting the quality standards.
- This was a very much hands on role where I would be coding with the team, and often parachuting to help.
- · I was also heavily involved in team growth and recruiting.
- The project was developed by following a Behavior-Driven Development (BDD) approach and agile techniques (Kanban).
- C#, .Net 4.5, MVC 4, Entity Framework 6.0, SpecFlow, Jenkins

Software Engineer 09/2012 – 12/2012 triAGENS Barcelona

- Worked as tech lead on an app called Instacard (https://itunes.apple.com/es/app/pixum-instacard-fotos-als/id547183491).
- I was responsible for all IOS development in ObjectiveC/Cocoa.
- I lead a team of external contractors on a very tight delivery schedule making sure we didn't compromise quality due to schedule constraints.
- I would often parachute to help fix critical issues like threading and memory consumption, both during development and in production.

 Software Engineer
 09/2011 – 08/2012

Spenta Consulting Barcelona

- Worked on Beezy (http://gobeezy.com/) a corporate social network implemented in Microsoft technologies.
- Developed the IOS client for Beezy.
- Championed XP Practices adoption in the company and technology changes that would break the dependency the solution had on SharePoint.
- My main challenge was to mentor/coach a team of very experienced SharePoint developers to break their ties with it and explore other designs/architectures.
- Implemented agile practices such as: Iteration planning, code refactoring, active stakeholder participation, burn down tracking, retrospectives, pair programming, daily stand up meetings, deliver frequently and development using BDD.
- Tools to support these practices: Jenkins, MSBuild, NUnit, Mercurial, RhinoMock, VS2010, Cucumber, XCode, RESTKit, Objective-C.

Product Leader 09/2010 – 05/2011

NTR Global Barcelona

- NTR was a Spanish startup that had had a very fast growth quickly expending into Europe, USA and Asia.
- They where a Logmein competitor offering a very similar product.
- When I joined, I found a burn out team that had taken massive tech debt.
- My immediate approach was to act as a team shield making sure they were able to work on a steady pace.
- This gave the team enough breathing space to start tackling the tech debt problem and go back to a more sane development cycle.
- My technical involvement was limited to high level architecture decisions.
- Main technologies: ASP.Net MVC, NHibernate, RabbitMQ, SQL Server, MongoDb, Javascript RIA.

Software Engineer 12/2008 – 09/2010

Spenta Consulting Barcelona

- Worked on a large eGovernment project for the Basque regional government lead by Microsoft.
- Implemented agile practices such as: Iteration planning, code refactoring, pair programming, daily stand up meetings, deliver frequently and development using TDD.
- Tools to support these practices: TFS 2008, MSBuild, MSTest, moq.

**2BeWiser** Europe

- Volvo IT (Gent, Belgium) 2008 Designed and developed a HR web based workflow solution.
- Philips PBC (Hilversum, Netherlands) 2005 Designed an orchestration solution to be used in a Serviced Oriented Architecture (SOA) framework for Philips Netherlands.
- Sogeti (Culemborg, Netherlands) 2004 Designed a solution for the Netherlands Post Office this solution used .Net in the client and J2EE for the server.
- MacGregor (Madrid, Spain) 2004 Worked in the Quick response queue unit, responsible for fixing the most urgent problems.
- VivaEstates (Marbella, Spain) 2004 Worked on a workflow solution for sales automation.
- Solvay (Lisbon, Portugal) 2003 Designed and developed a workflow solution for internal QA.

Tech Lead 05/2007 – 08/2008

Vueling Airlines Barcelona

- Lead the development of a SOA based solution for overnight ticket processing.
- In this project our main goal was to divide a monolithic legacy application into multiple autonomous services.
- The monolithic solution usually consumed 8-12 hours to process data generated during 24 hour periods of ticket reservations, new solution 5-15 minutes for the same workload.
- Apart from the performance boost the new solution was also more maintainable, unit tested, using a automated build and deploy, more scalable and more resilient to fails.
- Implemented agile practices such as: Iteration planning, code refactoring, active stakeholder participation, burn down tracking, retrospectives, pair programming, daily stand up meetings, deliver frequently and development using TDD.
- Tools: Nant, CruiseControl.NET, MSBuild, NUnit, MBUnit, SVN.

Sr. Solution Developer

**Avanade** Barcelona

Tech lead

 Software Engineer
 09/2005 – 08/2006

**Sogeti** Barcelona

- Main responsibility was to start a team focused on Microsoft technologies such as: .Net, Sharepoint and Biztalk.
- This team was responsible for winning and then successfully implement solutions in clients such as Fundacio La Caixa, Agencia Catalana de la Agua and Bancaja.

Trainer 12/2002 – 02/2004

**Rumos**Lisbon

- My main responsibilities involved training developers in Microsoft .Net Technologies; I worked as a freelance trainer for this company on a course-by-course contract.
- Courses lectured: MOC 2710, MOC 2557, MOC 2373, MOC 2524, MOC 2310, MOC 2389, MOC 2549, MOC 2565, MOC 2415, MOC 2350, MOC 1905

#### From Software engineer to Tech Lead

05/1994 – 12/2002

08/2006 - 05/2007

Infordesporto

Lsbon

- Design and development of software solutions for collecting and displaying sport statistics on TV and latter on the web.
- · http://www.ojogo.pt
- http://www.sporting.pt
- http://www.fcporto.pt
- http://noticias.uol.com.br/pelenet/

### **Education**

MSc, IT

University of Liverpool

09/2003 - 06/2006

10/1990 - 12/1993

**Bac, Managment** Universidade Lusofona

Lisbon

Concepção e Supervisão de Sistemas de Informação em Ambiente Apple/Macintosh, Information Technology- 12/1994 **FUNDETEC/RUMOS** Lisbon

Liverpool

HighSchool, HighSchool

01/1980 - 12/1989

Colégio Moderno

Lisbon

# **Certifications**

Microsoft Certified Solution Developer MCSD1: Microsoft .NET

## **Skills**

- Technology Leadership Coaching & Mentoring Big-Picture ThinkingC#Rust Typescript F# • Python • Distributed Systems Software Architecture Domain-Driven Design (DDD) • Test-Driven Development (TDD) • Cloud Platforms (AWS, Azure) • CI/CD • Test Automation Technical Coaching React.jsRefactoring Legacy Code Modernization
   Microservices Architecture XP Practices
- Behavior-Driven Development (BDD)
   Pair Programming Serverless Architecture